Emory University Faculty records, 1917-2002
Emory University
Emory University Faculty records, 1917-2002
Emory University.
Series No. 21
4 linear ft. (8 boxes)
The records of the Emory University Faculty document the faculty's role in the administration of the University. The records consist of by-laws, handbooks, minutes, subject files, and committee records. There is also information concerning faculty awards and chairs.
Emory University Emory University Archives
Source
Transfer.
Restrictions on Access
Unrestricted access.
Administrative History
Emory University faculty began teaching at Emory's Atlanta campus in 1919 after being officially transferred from Oxford, Georgia following Emory College's reincorporation as Emory University. Since then, they have been involved in the administration of the University, its teaching, and its students. The faculty are organized by school, each represented by a corresponding Dean.
Scope and Content Note
Emory University Faculty records contain administrative materials related to the faculty's role in the governance of Emory University. Contained in the collection are by-laws and policy documents related to faculty rights and privileges, minutes from faculty meetings, and materials from committees regarding diverse issues like curricula, retirement, academic standards, and campaign planning. Materials pertaining to various awards and chairs throughout the University, as well as subject files, are included in the collection.
Arrangement Note
Organized into four series: (1) General records, (2) Awards and Chairs, (3) Subject files, and (4) Committees.
Related Materials in This Repository
Emory College Faculty records (Series 52)
Selected Search Terms
Corporate Names
Emory University--Administration.; Emory University--Faculty--Retirement.; Emory University--Faculty Advisory Council.; Emory University--Curricula.
Topical Terms
College teachers--Georgia.; Universities and colleges--Administration.; Universities and colleges--Faculty.
Description of Series
- General records, 1917-2002, Series 1; Boxes 1-3
  - Bylaws, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Faculty handbook, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Faculty handbook, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Faculty handbook, 1993-94 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Faculty, new, 1947-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lists: College faculty, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lists: Department chairs, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lists: Undergraduate faculty council, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lists: University committees, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lists: Distinguished chairs at Emory, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorials, 1955-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1965-1966, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1977-1978, 1981, 1992, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Motions, 3 May 1960: Segregated education issues (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Policies, 1950-1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Club Minutes, 1918-1930 (Box BV1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, undated (Box BV2)
  - College Faculty Minutes, 1917-1930 (Box BV3)
- Awards and Chairs, 1962-2000, Series 2; Box 4
  - Charles Howard Candler Professorships, 1959-1960, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Charles Howard Candler Professorships, 1980, 1984, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Emory Williams Distinguished Teaching Award 1972-1973, 1977-1978, 1981, 1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fuller E. Callaway Professorships 1967, 1971, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Guggenheim fellows, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Robert W. Woodruff Lecture and Award, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Thomas Jefferson Award, 1962-2000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - United Methodist Church Award for University Scholar/Teacher, 1982, 1984, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Subject files, 1958-1988, Series 3; Box 4
  - Dekalb Superior Court case; Emory plaintiff, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Faculty discussion groups, 1975, 1981, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Faculty orientation, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Luce faculty seminar, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Statement by the Emory faculty on closing the public schools, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Symposium, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Wonderful Wednesday faculty questionnaire, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Committees, 1938-1994, Series 4; Boxes 5-8
  - Absences, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Academic progress measurement, [1932] (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Academic standards (also known as Academic policies and standards committee), 1959, 1962, 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Academic standards, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Academic standards, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Admissions and scholarship, 1959, 1962-1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Admissions and scholarship, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Afro-American studies (Curriculum) sub-committee, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Afro-American studies (Curriculum) sub-committee, 1970 January-March (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Afro-American studies (Curriculum) sub-committee, 1970 April-December (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Camp planning (Faculty-staff camp), 1953-1955, 1959-1966 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Camp planning, 1967-1968, 1972-1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Campaign planning, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Campaign planning, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - College environment, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Commencement, 1933-1958, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Community and relief funds, 1946-1947, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Curriculum, 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Curriculum, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Curriculum, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Curriculum, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Curriculum, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Curriculum, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Curriculum, 1967, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Curriculum, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Curriculum, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Curriculum, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Curriculum revision (ad hoc), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Development, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Educational policy, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Executive (Continues: Legislative council), 1970-1972 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Executive, 1973-1981, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Faculty advisory council, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Faculty advisory council, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Faculty advisory council, 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Faculty advisory council, 1980-1984, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Faculty organization study, 8 May 1958 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Freshman and sophomore advisory system, 1959, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Insurance, 1938, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Legislative council (Continued by: Executive committee), 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Legislative council, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Legislative council, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Legislative council, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Legislative council, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Legislative council, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. scholarship campaign, 1968, 1972-1973, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Morale (WWII), 1942, 1946, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Policies and principals, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Problems of plagiarism, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Public functions, 1938-1947, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Publicity, 1941-1942 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Religious discussion, 1953-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Retirement, 1938-1942-Minutes (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Retirement, 1938-1942-Correspondence and memoranda (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Retirement, 1939, 1941-Membership (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Retirement, 1937, 1941, undated-Retirement plan (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Retirement, 1941-Group insurance (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Retirement, undated-Faculty birth dates (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Scholarship, 1946-1961 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Task force on curriculum (clipping), 1994 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Three-year B. A. degree study (ad hoc), 1972 (Box 8, Folder 23)